[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a group of suttas that are basically on the same... talking about the same topic.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one is Angatranikāya, book of fives, number 151.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it says, because someone with five qualities isn't able to enter the sure path in regard to beneficial qualities, even when listening to the true teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: What five?
[SPEAKER_01]: They discredit the talk, the speaker, or themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: They listen with a scattered and distracted mind, and they attend not through the origin, which is ayoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone with these five qualities is unable to enter the sure path in regard to beneficial qualities, even when listening through teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, eh... someone with five qualities is able to enter the sure path in regard to beneficial qualities, when they have the opposite qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they don't discredit the talk, eh... the speaker or themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: They listen with an unscattered and unified mind, and they attend through the origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yonisona-sikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, maybe we can start with that one, because the other two have sort of a similar structure, but those five things are slightly varied.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: First of all,
[SPEAKER_01]: We should probably clarify, what does it mean to enter the sure path in the art of beneficial qualities?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, eh... you know, it's not just, eh... it shouldn't be minimized into just like, oh, I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I... now I agree with the Buddha's teaching or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... or... or even I took refuge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there were many instances in the suttas of people who factually said, I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I take refuge in the Buddha, Dhamma, Saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... they weren't in the sure path.
[SPEAKER_01]: In wholesome qualities, which means they were not guaranteed to become arahants, because they didn't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so that's basically also, like, the answer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, that particular phrase is a somewhat technical term, but I take it to mean the first of the eight kinds of individuals, of noble beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because then, you know, you can, to some extent, have, like, as it says, ayonisa manasikāra, so then, even if you don't have the other four,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you think the Buddha is the greatest, and you have a total conviction, but you don't have that yoniso recognition of where this teaching actually applies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, you will... As the Buddha said, there's the one who is padāpāna, which means like all he can do is learn the phrases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learn the kind of teachings and recite them and kind of talk about them, but not actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no actual purification taking place.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, as we often say, that right level hasn't been discerned.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those two teachings actually apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so what would be some of the most common ways that, you know, even though it's just someone would be listening to the true teaching, reading the sutras and whatnot,
[SPEAKER_01]: That they would be attending ayoniso, even in like just a very basic way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lack of restraint?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, yeah, that would be causing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But like, what would be the... more directly speaking, like... Like, while you are listening to someone else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what reasons, why, kind of frameworks of thought that you would have, that would prevent you from understanding?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing it as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even more, kind of, generally than that,
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so, you see, if one only listens to... and we are assuming that the speaker, that the other person, is actually proclaiming true dhamma and knows what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if one is hearing those words, but is just attending to those words, meaning it stays completely external, right, and you do not, let's say, simultaneously with what you hear,
[SPEAKER_04]: Also, observe all your own reactions to what you hear, or somebody uses a certain word, and you immediately connect it with, oh yeah, that other person has said the same thing, or I read that in a book a year ago, therefore, well, this is actually going to be the next one, but therefore, I have already understood it, but that mental movement
[SPEAKER_04]: It's almost completely taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: It goes so quickly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, either one stays completely on the external level and doesn't actually see where those words are supposed to land internally.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the intermediate step is to have those, let's say, both domains, to attend to them both at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it put in a more, even more simple terms that you don't see that this dhamma is about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about... because, you know, there are infinite ways that you can proliferate into, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, you know how they would connect it with all the science.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the same thing as the scientists are saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's already on the level of wrong views now, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're then, like, trying to find parallels between this school and that school and this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even with the suttas, actually, you know, there's now the whole kind of early Buddhist movement, which has its positives, obviously, because, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Disregarding a lot of the stuff that came later and muddles the actual message, but then you can see the same kind of, eh... ayoniso attitude remains in the form of now, like, oh, the sutta, you know, there has no parallel in the Chinese or then, you know, studying it and that kind of... That's actually another practical way in which you
[SPEAKER_04]: can tell that you are attending not from the origin.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is this attitude of comparison.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if if you find that you are comparing what you hear with something else, that means that that you have already externalized the message
[SPEAKER_04]: into an object that you can sort of put in front of you, and then compare it with something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: And meanwhile, you stay safely out of the equation, because you are just concerned with finding the connections there, whereas the whole message should be 90 degrees right the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to be comparing it with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm talking... the Buddha, as always, would be talking about greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I have those qualities?
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent do I have those qualities?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be a basic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, obviously, this is not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not talking about a super, kind of, accurate discernment of, you know, final impermanence and not-self or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just saying, oh, it's just a short path in regard to beneficial qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the very start of a path.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's so fundamental that, you know, if you skip that part, then even if later on you get all the information about anatta and all this and that, it's coming from the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also, maybe, we can say the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I have learned it like this from Nyanaviratera, when he was emphasizing on the subjective, compared
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, actually, that's that's one thing, because often it's thought like, okay, so, self has to be abandoned, kind of the message of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that means subjectivity has to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be perfectly objective.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when this sort of message comes in, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Ironically, like, that's completely the opposite of what it's saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take yourself out of the equation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't consider, like, you know, your mental states, your liabilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just this blank present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're all in the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: These impersonal kind of sensations, watching or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the the
[SPEAKER_01]: The essence of, like, craving, my craving, that I act out of, you know, that part is completely unaddressed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and if it would be on that level, then an average well-trained scientist, we would have some reports that they entered that path of security in an awesome state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because a perfectly objective individual, then, would be in the position to realize the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you have to start by taking it personally, ironically, and form within that subjective attitude, as you mentioned.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is where the purification needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you skip that first step, you basically don't even start.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, it always says, when somebody would start practice and, you know, become a monk, it would say that the clansman realizes that he's prey to suffering, he's subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not just like trying in that impersonal manner, like, oh, I want to find out whether this... have this curiosity, want to find out whether this teaching is true or not, in that kind of impersonal sense, so that then I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't make the comparisons with the other ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's I am prey to suffering and I need to find a solution for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that leads to the... well, it was actually the previous one, but we skipped on to the last one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's then when you would be kind of discrediting the speaker and the talk, because if you don't have the context of, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine you're looking for a cure for a disease.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you don't keep that in mind, you don't keep that as your background of, okay, this is what I'm going to this doctor, then you will be putting first a whole bunch of...
[SPEAKER_01]: There are sets of other things, like, oh, his attitude, the way he talks, secondary kind of considerations, and you'll be finding fault with, I mean, infinite amount of things, like, why did he spend such and such year, this amount of years in medical school instead of this other amount of years, like, random things you could start finding fault with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, or I don't like the way he talks, I don't like the way he looks.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can notice that, and so it's okay to not like it, but that's not the criteria for dismissing the validity of the message.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, again, like, if you have that urgency to find the way out of suffering, it should be pretty clear to you that
[SPEAKER_01]: If you allow yourself to use the criteria that you're used to, to determine what is worth following or not, you're most likely gonna, you know, pass over what was the true teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you have nothing to gain.
[SPEAKER_01]: From that kind of attitude of finding fault with the speaker, with the talk, because it's not going to help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's wrong, actually, it's not going to help you actually understand why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be just like, oh, I dismiss it again out of all these bunch of other reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you wouldn't be able to to kind of come up with a coherent explanation of, you know, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I see for myself why this doesn't solve the problem that I'm trying to solve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why does it need to be, etc.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so somebody might be giving a factually wrong message and it is... and to recognize a wrong view as wrong view is valid.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what is not valid is to have the mental state that is looking for faults in the speaker or the message.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are two different things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you don't need to have that mental attitude in order to see that something factual doesn't add up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, the criticism should be always about the view, and it shouldn't be about the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... And the one that says disparaging themselves, well, that's why it says that if the starting point of everything is virtue,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, when somebody is not established in virtue, they will not be free from regrets.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the... that's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: There was a case of that king who was... the king who murdered the previous king, who was his father.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, Dīgha Nikaya too.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha was kind of telling him... the whole dhamma, basically, explained to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, at the end of it, he said, oh, if he hadn't killed his father,
[SPEAKER_01]: He would have gained the right view right there, but he's now broken because of what he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he cannot be... that remorse, he cannot kind of grow out of it anymore because it's so kind of heavy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, looking in the direction, again, turning the dhamma into that personal dimension, like of great aversion and delusion, is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look what I did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that thought would be so unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, you know, they wouldn't be able to kind of, again, apply that yoniso and see, oh, yeah, I have to actually feel ashamed about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, that's why he wouldn't have been able to get the right view, because to some extent, even if there wasn't like that kind of overly coarse external scientific objective attitude that people might have today,
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, he had to kind of keep it at arm's length to some degree, so as to not feel the weight of his responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's in a sense why you need to be established in virtue, because, you know, yeah, it might not be... like that might have stopped him
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: For you, maybe something even lesser than that could be what stops you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such that, deep down, you still disparage... discredit yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you still have that sense of remorse on account of something that you know is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, you would maybe not even be fully aware of it, because that's how these things work.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cover them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... you don't want to admit them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, you have to go stronger in order to be with that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, dhamma has to be an opportunity to actually get a message.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says the only things that categorically stop everyone from...
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding dhamma is like killing your father, which is what he did, killing your mother, intentionally shedding the blood of the Tathāgata, violating a vikuni, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Killing an arhant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Killing an arhant, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so assuming that that's not the case, we can continue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so the second one says the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the five qualities are, again, discredit the talk, the speaker, or themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're witless, dull, and stupid.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fifth one, which is the most interesting one, they think they understand what they don't understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone with these five qualities isn't able to enter the sure path in regard to the official qualities even when listening to the true teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: The third one is they listen to the teaching with a hostile, fault-finding mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're antagonistic to the teacher, planning to attack them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're wordless, dull, and stupid.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, they don't understand what... they think they understand what they don't understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think attack there is like verbal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you just want to argue, have debates, and basically you want to prove your own points, which is somewhat ironic, because if that would be right, you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, you are...
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine, like, you go to this doctor and he's telling you the treatment, and you're trying to tell him what the treatment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that means, like, oh, you're not even honest about the fact that you are sick.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that you don't know the way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, yeah, you... Well, that ties in with saying, oh, he thinks he understands, when he doesn't actually understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would be probably one of the most prevalent attitudes, especially, again, because of the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, all of it ties in together, like, because of this whole objective attitude that, you know, if you just gather this information, and then, you know, everybody
[SPEAKER_01]: Other Buddhists say the same thing, and you agree, and that's that's kind of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, I understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, or it makes sense intellectually, but we didn't talk on how even the right ideas are not necessarily inside.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, you do need to have the right ideas and the right concepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to think in the right categories, but it's a mistake to stop on that level and not now go further.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think also, like, just hearing that, like, I can see that, like, the kind of tendency will be, okay, okay, so then I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, like, this kind of, I don't understand, can become what I think I do understand, in order to not feel the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not enough to say like, okay, I don't understand, like, I should... We were talking about that a little bit the other day, like, I should take on, like, if I really kind of acknowledge the fact that I don't understand, I should act as if I don't understand and not starting to...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of like, okay, I don't understand, but still, I'm doing this, I'm doing that, I'm doing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It kind of doesn't go together.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think Medini was also kind of nicely said, more or less, kind of this attitude of taking, like, I don't understand, in order to not feel the pressure of doubt, but actually, like, this recognition of, like, I don't understand,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not necessarily a pleasant thing to organize for oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that it doesn't become like an excuse for just doing...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I don't understand, so I just do whatever, hoping that understanding will magically arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, I don't understand and partially that's probably because of things I myself am doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then that should feel... Again, you should feel the responsibility for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because it would have said... Yeah, I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, beings are owners of their actions and, you know, all of the greed, aversion and delusion that you've accumulated, even if you don't remember all the things that you did, fundamentally, at that time, you chose to do those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the same way, yeah, you have to realize you don't understand it's because of... not necessarily because of things you're doing... did in the past, but because now that you have an option to go in a different direction, you still don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might be, you know, agreeing again with these external explanations of dhamma and whatnot, but okay, when it comes down to, do you act as if craving is the root of suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you live that view?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or is it just kind of... An idea disconnected from your daily life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can even see that, you know, this is what the Buddha is saying would lead to entering that short path in regard to skillful qualities, whereas
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, it would be like... the assumption would be, again, like a mindless practice of meditation, where, indeed, you would be assuming you understand what you don't understand, because, oh, I just do this?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to understand for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, what is wholesome, what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: I assume that this is already wholesome in and of itself, and I just do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, none of this... that's never mentioned here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the Buddha doesn't say you will fail to understand what you... you'll fail to understand dhamma because you're not sufficiently skilled in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people will usually assume, okay, yeah, I know, I kind of know the dhamma, you know, because I've been reading the suttas and, you know, practicing for God knows how many years.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because I haven't meditated enough, or consistently enough, or long enough retreat, I didn't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I haven't had that kind of special insight, that kind of experiential recognition of these things that I already understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, that's the mistake.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the confirmation that the method is right hasn't arrived yet, whereas actually the method itself is to understand what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of having that expectation, you should see, oh no, wait,
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I even right in assuming that this is the practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So... Yeah, but that is now going to be unpleasant, because you cannot now just disappear in your practice for an hour.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to now need to question... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: ...that very practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, a lot of this boils down to the ability to allow doubt to be present and to make that your vehicle until you find that which you cannot doubt, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: That is, in every single case, when you read the suttas, would lead to somebody getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's described there, it's yonisāṃsikāra and the utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like... because, yeah, literally, the way it's presented is like, no, no, you may not have heard anything, no utterance of another, no nothing, you just do this, boom, you get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, clearly here it's saying, if you have these attitudes that kind of obstruct your right acceptance of what, yes, initially is just information, then you will not get to understand that information.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the nature of understanding, if you think about it, it's like, you know, what is it that determines whether you understand some kind of mathematical theorem or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it that, oh, no, no, I understand it, but I still need to get the experience of something in order to understand it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, like, you know that you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you understand it, you know that you do understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's nothing more mystical about understanding the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be the measure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, of course, I say that, and then it sounds like, oh, so you're saying it's just intellectual kind of a recognition of things that are in existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, because how would you know that you actually understood the way of suffering?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, or that there isn't... or, you see, yes, or you might have been going in the right direction and see some benefit, but you didn't go far enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but yeah, how would you know that you're understanding
[SPEAKER_01]: of Four Noble Truths that, yes, everybody has, to some extent, because, you know, they've been reading the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that that's... how would you distinguish that between, let's say, insight and understanding, given that it's not just some experience that... because experiences aren't permanent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, let's say between ideas and insights.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, idea will be like the theoretical kind of thinking, and the insight will be like the direct recognition of...
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but then, but then, yeah, so how would you... because even, yeah, even an experience, magical experience, you might have had in your meditation, that doesn't mean you understood four of our truths, if we take it from this criteria, that are hinting at.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe, like, I just realized, I think, we'll be, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: If I'm in a kind of situation where I find myself suffering, like, I don't have to explain myself why is that happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: I kind of recognize it and I know, kind of, why is that there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but see, then even saying why is that there, that could mean, like, psychologicalization of like, oh yeah, but it's because
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is like this, and then this happens, and people start talking about mind elements, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, because what are the four noble truths?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just knowing what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm sure I understand the question now.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like... How do you know that you have fully understood the form of the truth?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or sufficiently, let's say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, sufficiently the form of the truth, so that it's not an idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because people can have the idea that craving is suffering, which is a right idea, but that doesn't mean that there is now no suffering anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just an idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the answer to your question is in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so basically, if there is still suffering, it doesn't matter if you have to explain it, if you have to review the information that you gain to kind of feel at ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a value management again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the measure for
[SPEAKER_01]: Actual understanding, yeah, it is kind of something you would be able to explain to somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that it's some kind of mystical, like, oh, I know it, but I can't explain it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or it is a nameless tooth, or it cannot be put into words, so you just use your mystifications.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is something you can you can explain, which is what the Buddha was doing the entire time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at the same time,
[SPEAKER_01]: The practical confirmation of it is that you don't suffer, factually, and that's what makes it experiential.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not some kind of medical insight or, again, mystical, sort of, oh, I saw the final truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, it is like, throughout your day, when you encounter things that confine your mind and make it feel kind of like
[SPEAKER_01]: burdened and weighed down, are you affected?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you get to see whether it's just information or whether it's actually understanding the way I was suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, yeah, it's not about just using the information to kind of manage the suffering after the fact, because from that point of view, I mean, millions of teachings can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just convince yourself that God loves you or something, and that has exactly the same effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dhamma is the only teaching that doesn't require even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's suffering not arising in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you say when the mind is still weighed down, constricted, I guess, by whatever...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the final insight that the Buddha had.
[SPEAKER_02]: There were other ascetics and brahmins that would factually teach the taming of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only one who actually taught the complete transcending of the appropriation was the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that's why, even when, yeah, your mind factually... Actually, that's quite a good distinction between... Because, yeah, you could even use the virtue as a form of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's the right management that will help you understand dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, without virtue, there can be no dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, as the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is not virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you have to realize, oh, is it, yeah, is it that I suffer, that I'm free from suffering only because I'm kind of so withdrawn from all these things, from, you know, sense objects and sensuality, in the right way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it because even if I were to completely just
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, let go of the practice, then nothing would arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you had developed yourself properly, you wouldn't be able to do certain things anymore, as the Buddha said, and cannot break the the precepts and cannot break celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but yeah, then, that's why, eh... fundamentally, as the Buddha said, eh... samādhi, which you could say is like the mind being tamed or being pliable, eh... that's not the hardwood.
[SPEAKER_01]: of the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like irreversible liberation, which he called like the unshakable liberation of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the essence of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is really the final non-management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as he said, even putridionists, who obviously would still be dependent on management to some degree, they could still
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, attain the right kind of samādhi and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that now, the management is like even of a lesser... like it's not even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even like taming the mind, it's just ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why... yeah, then... then... it's not even helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, even the right management of taming the mind in the right way,
[SPEAKER_01]: That will be transcended by the understanding of the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, as to say, they would... like the... the arahant would continue practicing samādhi only for kind of a pleasant abiding here and now, or for kind of a example for future generations, but not because it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like... like a... a patronina who hasn't understood the... that fact of cessation, be like, no, no, I have to keep doing this forever.